Lillian Moller Gilbreth Papers, 1860-1999
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Lillian Moller Gilbreth papers
1860 - 1999
Gilbreth, Lillian Moller, 1878-1972
374
17 boxes (8.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Industrial engineer. In addition to industrial engineering, Gilbreth and her husband published and lectured extensively on the subject of motion saving techniques and worker efficiency with respect to both physical ability and psychological variables. Family material reflects the unique Gilbreth method of child-rearing. The bulk of the family correspondence is with Gilbreth's third daughter, Ernestine Gilbreth Carey. Other materials include awards, photographs, writings and speeches.
Lillian Moller Gilbreth is perhaps most widely known as the mother of the Cheaper by the Dozen family but her talent and groundbreaking influence in the field of industrial engineering is her most remarkable achievement. Lillian Moller was born in 1878 to William Moller, a partner in a large retail hardware business, and Annie Delger. As a youth, she became interested in poetry and pursued her passion as an undergraduate. In 1900, Lillian Moller graduated from the University of California with a degree in British literature. She then attended Columbia University for graduate study in English literature. Two years later she was awarded a Master's degree. In 1903, she met Frank Bunker Gilbreth, a cousin of her chaperone. Frank Gilbreth had risen from an apprentice bricklayer to become a well-known contractor through his labor-saving techniques and ingenuity. The couple married in 1904 and soon thereafter embarked upon a joint career in industrial engineering. After publishing two books, Motion Study (1911) and Primer of Scientific Management (1912), the couple moved from Boston to Providence, Rhode Island where they founded Gilbreth, Incorporated, a consulting engineering firm. Lillian M. Gilbreth received her Ph.D. in industrial psychology from Brown University in 1915. Lillian and Frank Gilbreth were popular lecturers and spoke at many conventions and universities on the subject of motion saving techniques and worker efficiency with respect to both physical ability and psychological variables. Lillian Gilbreth stressed the "human element in management" and believed that the individual worker was more responsive to recognition of good performance than to threats of punishment. This type of positive discipline was integral to the Gilbreth method of management, which they practiced both professionally and also in their domestic life. Between 1905 and 1922, Lillian Gilbreth gave birth to twelve children, eleven of whom survived to adulthood. In 1924, Frank Gilbreth died suddenly of a heart attack. Lillian attempted to continue their consulting business. She experienced so much discrimination in her attempt to go solo in an overwhelmingly male profession, that she began concentrating on issues of homemaking. Gilbreth published two books on the subject, The Home-Maker and Her Job (1927) and Management in the Home (1954). Gilbreth and her husband were also concerned with the needs of disabled individuals. While he was still alive, they published several articles on disabled soldiers and Gilbreth continued this thread by designing equipment and motion saving methods to make household tasks easier for disabled people. She also published two books on this subject, Normal Lives for the Disabled (1933) which she co-authored with Edna Yost, her friend and later biographer, and Straight Talk for Disabled Veterans (1945). Despite the obstacles faced by a woman in the field of engineering, Gilbreth's career flourished. She was appointed professor of management at Purdue University in 1935 and also was a member of the faculty at Newark College of Engineering from 1941-43. She also volunteered for many groups and organizations, including the Girl Scouts of America. Throughout her career, Gilbreth won many awards and was a popular speaker. She died in 1972 at the age of 83.
For more information, see Jane Lancaster's dissertation, Wasn't She the Mother in Cheaper by Dozen: A Life of Lillian Moller Gilbreth, 1878-1972 (1998); Laurel Graham's book, Managing on Her Own (1998); and the American National Biography and Notable American Women.
The Lillian Moller Gilbreth Papers consist of 6.5 linear feet of material dating from the late 1860s through 1999. The collection contains both personal and professional papers. Ernestine Gilbreth Carey, her third daughter, has been instrumental in both the documentation and publicity of her mother's career. Carey is the author of two books that describe her unusual upbringing, Cheaper by the Dozen (1948), which she co-authored with her brother Frank Gilbreth, Jr., and Belles on Their Toes (1950). Carey gathered most of the material in this collection in preparation for a biography of her mother. Many of the documents contain notes that reflect Carey's process as a writer and researcher.
The Lillian Moller Gilbreth Papers at the Sophia Smith Collection are closely associated with the Ernestine Gilbreth Carey Papers also housed here. A more extensive archive of Lillian Gilbreth is located in the Department of Special Collections and Archives at Purdue University Library.
This collection is organized into six series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Speeches and Writings
IV. Organizations and Professional Activities
V. Photographs
VI. Oversize Materials
BOOKS ON SHELF
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Ernestine Gilbreth Carey (Smith 1929) donated the material in this collection over the course of several years.
Search Terms
Carey, Ernestine Gilbreth, 1908-; Gilbreth, Frank B. (Frank Bunker), 1911-; Gilbreth, Lillian Moller, 1878-1972; Gilbreth, Frank Bunker, 1868-1924; Cheaper by the Dozen--Sources; Gilbreth family; Authors, American--20th century--Sources; Censorship--United States--20th century; Family--United States--History--20th century-Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material can be found in the Ernestine Gilbreth Carey Papers, Sophia Smith Collection. Additional papers of Lillian Gilbreth are in the Department of Special Collections and Archives, Purdue University Library.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1905-99, undated, 2.75 linear ft
  The material in this series is divided into five subseries: General, Writings about Gilbreth, Family, Death, and Awards, commemorations, remembrances, and tributes. The material under the General heading includes notebooks, memorabilia, date books, address books, itineraries, and a curriculum vita.
  The Writings about Gilbreth are rather extensive and include scholarly works, articles published in trade magazines, works representing the influence of the Gilbreth method in the field of management, and newspaper clippings. Of particular interest are the scholarly writings by Laurel D. Graham, which discuss Gilbreth's career and the extent of her influence.
  The material pertaining to the Gilbreth Family includes a family log, a variety of recollections, and material that reflects the unique Gilbreth method of child-rearing. The daily schedules, typewriting instructions, and especially the "Bi-Man" and "The Ambidextrous" magazines created by the children reflect the ways in which the emphasis on efficient time and motion management characterized the Gilbreth home.
  The subseries that pertains to Gilbreth's Death is comprised mainly of obituaries, numerous letters of condolence, and memorial gifts. Arranged alphabetically, the final subsereries, Awards, commemorations, remembrance, and tributes, accounts for nearly half of all the biographical material contained in this series. While Gilbreth received many honors and awards during her lifetime, the bulk of the material represents posthumous recognition. Especially noteworthy is the material pertaining to the 1984 Gilbreth commemorative stamp; Ernestine Carey, Gilbreth's daughter, spearheaded this initiative and the organizational schemes of many of the letters and virtually all of the notes pertaining to this endeavor are Carey's creation.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1879-1984, undated, 2 linear ft.
  This series is divided into two subseries, Family and Friends and associates. While there is some correspondence between Gilbreth and her sister, Annie Moller Cross, her husband, and her other children, the bulk of the family correspondence is with her daughter, Ernestine Gilbreth Carey [closed until 2013], dating from 1925, when Carey was a student at Smith College, to 1968, at which point the ailing Gilbreth moved in with her daughter, Ernestine Carey, before taking up her final residence at the Beatitudes nursing home.
  The correspondence between Gilbreth and her Friends and associates is sparse, with the exceptions of that with her most prominent protégé, Bo Casten Carlberg, and her long-time friend, Jewel C. Hardkopf.
- SERIES III. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS 1915-67, undated, 1 linear ft.
  This series is organized into two subseries, Speeches and Writings. The transcripts of her speeches span the dates of her solo career and provide excellent insight into the specifics of her management theories; they also offer a glimpse of her personality. Gilbreth's personal life is more apparent in her autobiographical writings and the memoir of her husband, The Quest for the One Best Way. This subseries also contains professional writings she authored individually and a selection of those she wrote in collaboration with her husband. Some of the latter bear only the name of Frank Gilbreth as author. These are included because, as Frank himself acknowledged, Lillian's professional input was a factor in virtually everything he published.
- SERIES IV. ORGANIZATIONS AND PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1924-81, undated, .25 linear ft.
  This series is divided into the subseries Organizations and Professional activities. Organizations includes reports, programs, and printed material from four professional organizations of which Gilbreth was a member. The material regarding Gilbreth's Professional activities relates her to household innovations and includes printed material, newspaper clippings, articles, and notes by Ernestine Carey.
- SERIES V. PHOTOGRAPHS circa 1860s-1996, .5 linear feet
  The photographs in this series include portraits of Gilbreth alone as well as photographs that document her wedding, various family members, residences, and aspects of her professional life.
  There are also many photographs documenting the ceremonies that honored Gilbreth after her death. Of particular interest are the numerous images of the eleven surviving Gilbreth children gathered together at the commemorative stamp ceremony.
- SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS 1904-1995, undated
  This series contains an assortment of memorabilia, including Gilbreth's National Women's Hall of Fame medal, material from her wedding gown, a sewing bag, house keys, and a turquoise beret, among other items. Also of interest is the undated 16 mm filmstrip of Gilbreth's speech at Waseda University in Tokyo.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - General
    - Fact sheet, circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Curriculum vita, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notebook, 1945-circa 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Datebook, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Address books, 1967-71 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Itinerary, 1965, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Beatitudes nursing home guest book, 1969-72 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1962, 1969-72, undated, [see also SERIES VI. OVERSIZED MATERIAL] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writings about Gilbreth
    - Scholarly works
      - General, 1983-95, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Laurel D. Graham
        - Articles, 1992-99 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Lillian Moller Gilbreth's extensions of scientific management into women's work, 1924-1935, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Articles
      - General, 1923-96, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Journal of Industrial Engineering, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - The Gilbreth Story, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Writings pertaining to Gilbreth's influence on management methods
      - General (includes Carlberg), 1912-92, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Frank Gilbreth, Inc., 1923 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Foreign language volumes, 1976, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1923-93, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Family
    - Marriage announcement, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Family log, 1923-56 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Frank Gilbreth's death, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous recollections, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Children
      - Birth announcements and list, 1905, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Daily schedules, 1916, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Typewriting instructions and poem, 1916, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - "The Ambidextrous Magazine," vol. IV no. I, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
      - "Bi-Man Magazine," 1922-23 (Box 3, Folder 10-19)
      - Frank Gilbreth, Jr.
        - Correspondence regarding Time Out for Happiness, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        - "Just Me," xeroxed copies of Frank Bunker Gilbreth's autobiographical notes and sketches of childhood, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Death
    - Legal documents, 1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Obituaries
      - Newspaper clippings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Professional organizations, 1972-74 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Memorial services and arrangements, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Contacts, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Letters of condolence
      - A-H, 1972-74 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - The Heath School, Margaret Firman's 4th and 5th graders, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - I-Z, 1972-73 (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
      - Telegrams, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Memorial gifts
      - General, 1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Purdue University Library, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Society of American Women Engineers, circa 1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Awards, commemorations, remembrances, and tributes
    - American Institute of Industrial Engineers, "The Frank and Lillian Gilbreth Conference": program and publicity, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME)
      - Honorary membership award, 1944-50 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Frank Gilbreth Centennial Conference, 1968
        - Program (Box 5, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 4)
        - Tributes and reminiscences (Box 5, Folder 5)
        - Scholarly papers (Box 5, Folder 6)
        - Exhibit (Box 5, Folder 7)
        - Newspaper clippings and articles, 1968-89 (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - Seating arrangement (Box 5, Folder 9)
        - Notes (EGC), undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Beatitude library memorial exhibit, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - CIOS gold medal award: transcript of speech and article, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Commemorative postage stamp
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1982-84, undated (Box 5, Folder 13-15)
        - Family, 1982-83, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
        - Robert S. Dunham (family friend), 1981-82 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Endorsements
        - Solicitations, contacts, and notes, 1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
        - Individuals
          - General, 1982-84, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
          - Helen B. Schleman (Dean of Women at Purdue, 1947-68), 1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Groups and organizations
          - Seventh grade students, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
          - New Jersey organizations, 1982-84 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Indexed correspondence, 1982-84 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
      - Publicity, 1983-84, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Postage stamp, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Commemorative stamp ceremony, 1984
        - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 8)
        - Guest book (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1981-91, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Catalogs, 1984-91 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Materials for commemorative plaque of stamp, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous notes (EGC), undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Gilbreth Medal, Society for Advancement of Management (SAM)
      - International Awards Programs and Professional Membership Grades Guidelines, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Recipients
        - 1931-90 s, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 15)
        - Ernestine Gilbreth Carey
          - Correspondence
            - Family, 1995-96 (Box 6, Folder 16)
            - SAM officials, 1972-96, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
          - Program and conference material
            - General, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 1)
            - Speech notes, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 2)
          - Miscellaneous notes and articles (EGC), 1982- circa 1996 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Publications, 1969-88, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Girl Scout Tribute, [see also SERIES V. PHOTOGRAPHS]
      - General: article, correspondence, program, reminiscences, and resolution, 1969-72, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence with Ernestine Carey, 1984, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Montclair Chamber of Commerce Award: correspondence, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - National Women's Hall of Fame induction, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Southern California Work Simplification Association, "The Frank and Lillian Gilbreth Conference": program and publicity, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - "That Reminds Me," anecdotes and recollections of Lillian Gilbreth, 1958-59 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous awards, tributes, etc. 1933-95 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Family
    - Bunker, Minnie (cousin), 1924-58 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Gilbreth, Frank Bunker, 1904-17 (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
    - Moller, Annie Degler (LMG's mother), [CLOSED until 2013]
      - 1879-81 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
      - 1882, undated (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - Notes on correspondence (EGC), undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Children
      - Carey, Ernestine Gilbreth, [CLOSED until 2013]
        - 1925-28 (Box 8, Folder 7-13)
        - 1929-62 (Box 9, Folder 1-9)
        - 1963-68, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
        - Re: Beatitudes Gilbreth exhibit and misc., 1973, 1984, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - Transcripts and editorial comments of select pieces of Lillian Gilbreth's correspondence (EGC), undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Gilbreth, Anne, 1927, 1940, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Gilbreth, Frank Jr., circa 1940s-60 s (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Gilbreth, Martha, 1943-44 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - From children, 1924-28 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - To children, 1943-44, circa 1950s-60s (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - To "Family," 1929, 1965-66 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
    - Grandchildren, 1955, 1967-68, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1868, 1904, 1914, 1940s (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Friends and associates
    - General, 1928-48, 1956-70, n.d (Box 11, Folder 10-11)
    - Individuals
      - Callaghan (?), Jane (secretary to Gilbreth), 1958 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Carlberg, Bo Casten
        - 1945-68 (Box 11, Folder 13-17)
        - From various Gilbreths (not Lillian), 1969-71 (Box 11, Folder 18)
        - Notes and transcripts of correspondence (EGC), undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - Hardkopf, Jewel C.
        - 1948-57 (Box 11, Folder 20-21)
        - 1958-68 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
      - Hilton, Eunice, 1949, 1954, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Kersting, Fred, 1962-68 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - May, Dr. Elizabeth, 1964-69 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Merrill, Dot, 1952-60 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Parker, Rachel, 1964-68 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Sanger, Margaret, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Schwab, Jack, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Witte, Irene, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- SERIES III. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  - Speeches
    - Index and brochure, 1962, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Transcripts, 1927-67, undated (Box 13, Folder 2-5)
    - 16 mm film recording of speech at Waseda University, Tokyo, undated, [see SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 13)
  - Writings
    - Lillian Gilbreth
      - Professional
        - List, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
        - Articles, 1926-64, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
        - "Suggestions for Taking Examinations" and "How Can We Get More and Better Executives," undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Autobiographical
        - Untitled, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
        - "My Home Town," undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Lillian and Frank Gilbreth
      - Articles, 1916-21, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - "Motion Study for the Handicapped," 1920 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Frank Gilbreth
      - Articles, 1915-23, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Film brochures, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
- SERIES IV. ORGANIZATIONS AND PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Organizations
    - American Society of Mechanical Engineers: report, 1968-69 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Centennial of Engineering: convocation program, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Conseil International pour l'Organisation Scientifique (CIOS)
      - General, 1924-67 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - 13th Congress, 1963, [see also SERIES V. PHOTOGRAPHS] (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Ernestine Carey's notes and research materials, 1975-81, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - National Academy of Engineering: membership book and 10th anniversary report, 1970, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Professional activities
    - Gilbreth management desk: printed material, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Kitchens
      - Kitchen Practical: articles, printed material, 1931, 1955 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Heart Kitchens, newspaper clippings, printed material, notes by Ernestine Carey, 1954, 1972-83, undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Fatigue laboratory, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous printed material, 1930, undated (Box 14, Folder 15)
- SERIES V. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Wedding to Frank Bunker Gilbreth, 1904 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Gilbreth alone
    - Standing barefoot on Nantucket, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Seated on bench, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Standing in Tokyo, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Looking at portrait of mother, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Headshot, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Family
    - All together, circa 1920 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Children, 1916, circa 1940s and 1980s (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Extended family, circa 1860s-1910 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Frank Gilbreth, circa 1920s (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Photographs removed from Gilbreth's datebook, 1968
    - Frank Gilbreth, 1923 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Jane Callaghan, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Rebecca (grandchild?), 1968 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Gilbreth matriarch and Mary, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Teddy, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Gilbreth with Ray Shafer and R.D. Fowler, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Boy with rabbits and gun, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified woman, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Residences
    - Buttonwoods, New York, 1916 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - The Moller house, California, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - "The Shoe," Gilbreth Nantucket summer house interior, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - "The Shoe," exterior, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Awards, commemorations, remembrances, and tributes
    - Beatitudes exhibit, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Commemorative stamp ceremony, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Gilbreth Medal exhibit, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Girl Scout birthday tribute, 1984 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Professional
    - General, 1964-67, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - 13th CIOS Congress, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- SERIES VI. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Gilbreth's wedding dress material and lace, circa 1904 (Box 15a)
  - National Women's Hall of Fame Medal, 1995 (Box 15a)